When writing research papers, some people like to write in passive voice, and others
Khi viết các tài liệu nghiên cứu, một số người hay thiên về sử dụng cấu trúc câu bị động
prefer active voice.
và một số người khác thì ngược lại, thích dùng câu chủ động
So, what do we mean by this?
Vậy, vấn đề mà chúng ta đang nói ở đây là gì?
Well, this sentence, “This paper was read by a team of researchers.”, has been written
Ta hãy đến với 1 ví dụ, “This paper was read by a team of researchers.”
in a passive voice.
là câu được viết theo thể bị động
The subject in this sentence is “this paper”.
chủ ngữ ở đây là “this paper”
Whereas, “A team of researchers have read this paper.”, has been written in an active
trong khi ngược lại khi chuyển câu này sang bị động, ta lại có “A team of researchers have read this paper.”
voice.
voice.
The subject in this sentence is “a team of researchers”.
Chủ ngữ của câu là “a team of researchers”.
So, if the subject is performing the action, then it’s an active voice.
Vậy, nếu chủ ngữ là chủ thể của hành động thì câu đó được viết bằng thể chủ động
If the subject is having the action done to it, then it’s a passive voice.
Hoặc, nếu chủ ngữ là chủ thể chịu tác động của hành động, thì đó là thể bị động
In a sentence, the word “By” often suggests that a passive voice is being used.
Từ "by" là một dấu hiệu giúp ta có thể nhận biết đâu là câu bị động
As a funny, but useful tip, if you’re able to add the phrase “by zombies” at the
Hãy đến với 1 ví dụ vui nhưng cũng rất hữu ích , nếu bạn có thể làm câu có nghĩa bằng cách thêm cụm từ “by zombies” ở cuối câu
end of your sentence, then you have written the sentence in a passive voice.
Thì bạn đã viết ra được 1 câu bị động.
For example, this sentence, “The questionnaire was administered to participants in a lab….
hãy thử một ví dụ “The questionnaire was administered to participants in a lab…
By zombies”, has been written in a passive voice.
By zombies”, câu này là câu bị động.
Sometimes, we can use passive voice when we want to direct our focus on the object or
Thỉnh thoảng, chúng ta sử dụng thể bị động khi muốn nhấn mạnh vào tân ngữ
the recipient of the action as opposed to the individual person.
hay vật thể chịu sự tác động của hành động hơn là một con người cụ thể
For example, “The participants were instructed to read a questionnaire” emphasises the
Câu “The participants were instructed to read a questionnaire” nhấn mạnh
reading of the questionnaire, and not so much on who actually gave the instructions.
hành động "reading of the questionnaire" và không tập trung nhiều vào chủ thể đưa ra yêu cầu - gave instructions cho participants
However in most cases, active voice can be more engaging for your readers.
Tuy nhiên trong đa số trường hợp, thể chủ động lại lôi cuốn người đọc hơn
It’s not necessarily wrong to write in a passive voice, it’s just that sentences
Việc dùng thể bị đông không có gì là sai, nó đơn giản sẽ
written in a passive voice tend to be longer and less direct compared to those written
khiến cho câu có vẻ dài hơn và gián tiếp hơn
in an active voice.
là thể chủ động